Oliver Diamond

I am a senior (lead) full-stack Node/React software developer with an eclectic career. I have experience in many languages and technologies - and in approaches that emphasise microservices, devops, CI/CD, small iterations, and FP. Recently I have been focussing on how to grow dev teams, and how to prioritise business value vs tech debt.

- Current Position: Lead Developer, Tempo UK
- Specialisms: Node, React, Mongo, Microservices, K8s, mentoring juniors
- Passions: Linux, functional programming, point-free programming, devops, Spacemacs.
- Physics, 2:1 Imperial College London (specialism: Computational Simulations)
- Extensive experience outside programming: Finance, Politics, Media, Communications

Overview

Currently I work as Lead Developer at Tempo UK, with responsibility for building and maintaining the entire digital product. My efforts are focussed on breaking our monolith into microservices (leveraging Jenkins-X & Kubernetes), growing a culture of best practices within the dev team (FP, testing, code quality, latest tech, & mentoring juniors), and breaking apart the developers into smaller domain-focussed teams.

Prior to Tempo, I have most recently worked for for Sky, TES (formerly the Times Education Supplement) and HSBC. At home I'm also a tinkerer: RPis everywhere. I built a bare-bones K8s lab in my attic. I wrote a K8s CI/CD platform builder.

I follow leaders such as: Robert C Martin Martin Fowler, Fred George, Rich Hickey, & Sandi Metz. And I follow closely developments in the tech I have invested in: React, Redux, Node, GraphQL, K8s, GoLang, TypeScript, & JenkinsX.

Skills

Programming:

- JavaScript (ES6+, Node/React) 7+ yrs Microservices & Cloud (Mongo, SQL, Express, React, Redux, GraphQL, RabbitMQ, Webpack, Babel) • Continuous Delivery (Jenkins-X,
- Clojure (Compojure) 1+ yrs
- Java (Android, Spring) 2+ yrs
- · Ruby (Rails),
- Python (Django)
- C++

Delivery/Ops:

- (Kubernetes, Docker, GCP)
- Jenkins)
- Version control (Git, RTC)
- Linux (Ubuntu, Redhat, Debian)
- Spacemacs (Emacs + Vim), Eclipse, Intellil, Android Studio

Methodologies:

- Agile (Scrum, Kanban, Programmer Anarchy, lots of retrospecting)
- Devops (CI/CD)
- Test Driven Development
- Pair Programming
- Microservice Architectures
- Functional Programming (Point Free Programming)

Other Expertise

Government: I have 8 years experience across Government, public policy, and the digital & creative industries.

Finance: Aside from my tech work in HSBC's FX dept, I have experience as an analyst in hedge-funds and brokerages.

Communications: I have worked on public policy campaigns, in political comms, and in film & theatre marketing.

Work History

Tempo UK (July 2019 - present) | LEAD DEVELOPER

At Tempo I am responsible for the entire digital product. I manage a team of 6+ full-stack React/Node.js developers, with always ~50% junior/beginners.

I am taking Tempo from a start-up to a medium-sized tech company. While always being available to mentor and assist members of my team, I have concentrated efforts on introducing and leveraging technologies and practices that scale effectively. I have fostered a culture of collaboration, functional programming, end-to-end testing, clean code, domain driven design, continuous delivery, microservices, Kubernetes, GraphQL, event driven architectures.

My team have done this while continuing to deliver value - and demonstrating to investors the platform's ability to scale with only small increases in infrastructure costs.

Sky (May 2018 - July 2019) | SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Our team developed and maintained a suite of services that allow Sky's Editors to generate and publish scheduled menu changes and then serve it to ~6 million Set-Top-Boxes across the UK, Ireland, Germany, and Italy. As the team's Senior Engineer, I was responsible for directing the dev team's efforts; I prompt choices in technology, practices, and methodologies, aiming to facilitate my colleagues' work. As one of the only full-stack teams in Sky, we had concerns from hosting infrastructure to api resilience, to browser comparability. I also focussed on mentoring the junior and beginner developers across Sky - teaching beginners and leading workshops on clean code, and new technologies.

Tes Engineering (Oct 2017 - May 2018) | SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Tes (once the Times Education Supplement) provides teaching resources to most teachers in the UK. The company used microservices, with (mostly) a MERN stack (MongoDB, Express, React, Node), and had invested heavily in the concept of micro-frontends. Teams and services were divided by domain concerns, and I worked on reference checking, supply teacher sourcing and an end-to-end timesheets application.

HSBC GFX (Dec 2016 - Sept 2017) | DIGITAL TRANSFORMATION SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

My team of 6 delivered a suite of microservices in Clojure and ES6 and patched them into a legacy Java 6 / dojo.js monolith. We worked from within the modern foriegn-exchange department of the investment bank (GFX), making their products available via HSBCnet: one of the world's most used commercial payment platforms.

Makers Academy (May 2016 - Sept 2017) | SOFTWARE ENGINEERING CONSULTANT

London's top dev bootcamp. I was involved from the beginning in Makers Academy's consultancy arm which aimed to take freshly trained junior devs and place them in teams with Makers Academy corportate partners. True to the MA spirit, I also completed the Makers Academy course - a bootcamp focusing on professional programming best practices (Agile, TDD, BDD, Pair Programming and the).

Bob & Co (Nov 2014 - May 2016) | HEAD OF DIGITAL AND COMMUNICATIONS

A small media (film, TV, theatre) developer, and financier. I ran the technological, research & communication efforts.

SUMS Film & Media (Aug 2015 - Dec 2015) | DIGITAL CONSULTANT

An independent film producer. I advised the Chief Exec on digital strategies (IMDB ← I'm three clicks from Tom Cruise!).

North Square Blue Oak (Jan 2014 - Mar 2014) | ANALYST

A brokerage and corporate finance boutique. I assessed new opportunities in the digital and media sectors.

CQS Asset Management (Feb 2013 - Mar 2013) | *MARGINS DEPT ANALYST & SOFTWARE DEVELOPER* A \$13bn credit hedge fund. I worked in liability management and also with the strategic IT team

Office of the Digital & Cultural Minister (Nov 2008 - Nov 2014) | SENIOR PARLIAMENTARY ADVISOR I managed the Parliamentary Office of Rt. Hon. Ed Vaizey MP from before his Ministerial appointment. I oversaw the running of the office, interviewing, training and managing all junior staff. I worked on campaigns such as improving WiFi provision in public libraries and adding coding into the national curriculum.

Education

Physics 2:1 (BSc & ARCS): Imperial College London (Oct 2005 - July 2008)

I focussed on computational simulations, astrophysics, plasma physics, and the practicalities of nuclear fusion energy as a future energy source.

Final Year Degree Project (C++)

I received 93% for an computer simulation investigation into the process of evolution. I wrote the program from scratch, modelling biological systems. I was praised particularly for analysing great amounts of data, spotting patterns and anomalies, presenting them accessibly and quantifying the results in a manner that the department had never seen before.

Other Interests

CACIN - The Political Creative Industries Network (2008 - 2017) | DIRECTOR

I developed and maintained relationships with many key players in the tech & creative sectors on behalf Damian Collins MP, the Rt Hon Minister Ed Vaizey MP, and the Conservative Party HQ. I ran regular panels, drinks receptions and conferences across the UK, focusing on issues from the digital single market to diversity in the media.

The Digital Bazaar, Tate South Lambeth Library (2009 – 2013) | *FOUNDING VOLUNTEER & IT EXPERT* Taught basic computer skills, smartphone, and other technology use to struggling members of the Lambeth community (many of whom did not have English as a first language). Runners-up for the CILIP Libraries Change Lives Award 2012.

Music - I have an intensely musical education. A music scholarship took me through secondary school. I sang in Christ Church Cathedral Choir, Oxford (we sang the credits to Blackadder and Vicar of Dibley; we performed in front of HM the queen; and we toured the USA, Japan, Germany, France, and Brazil). I also played the Saxophone, Violin, Piano, and quitar.

Cooking - I love cooking and spend a great deal of time in the kitchen. I have been paid to cook at events. And my recipes are popular on Instagram.

Tennis - I play regularly with a variety of partners and am coached professionally.